GEORGIOS E. MAGDIS

Associate Professor

Cosmic DAWN Center (DTU-Space/DTU - NBI/KU)

email: geoma@space-dtu.dk Tel: +45-53775257

web: http://www.georgiosmagdis.com/ ORCID: https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4872-2294

RESEARCH PROFILE

I am an associate professor of extragalactic astrophysics and co-founder and deputy director of the DNRF Cosmic DAWN Center of Excellence at DTU-Space/DTU and NBI/KU. Additionally, I am leading a research group, funded by my Villum Young Investigator and Villum Young Investigator PLUS grants. The primary goals of my academic activities are to shed light on our cosmic origins by exploring the formation and evolution of the building blocks of our Universe and to educate, promote, and inspire the next generation of scientists.

EDUCATION

University of Oxford, UK	11/2010
DPhil in Astrophysics	
University of Crete, GR	09/2005
MSc in Astrophysics	
University of Crete, GR	09/2003
BSc in Physics	

ACADEMIC POSITIONS

Technical University of Denmark, DTU-Space/Cosmic Dawn Center Associate Professor	2019 - present
University of Copenhagen, Niels Bohr Institute/Cosmic Dawn Center	2019 - present
Affiliate Professor	
University of Copenhagen, Niels Bohr Institute/DARK Cosmology Center	er 2015 - 2019
Assistant Professor - Carlsberg/DARK Fellow	
University of Oxford, UK April 2011	! - November 2015
Research Fellow	
Service d'Astrophysique, CEA, Saclay, FR	2008 - 2011
Post-doctoral Researcher	

GRANTS/FUNDING

Young Investigator Program Plus, Villum Foundation, €700K (PI)	2021 - 2024	
The Hidden Cosmos; Tracing star formation and heavy element production in the early	Universe	
Centers of Excellence, DNRF €8.7million (co-founder/deputy director)	2018 - 2024	
Cosmic Dawn Center of Excellence		
Marie Curie Post Doctoral Fellowship, EU, €250K (Project supervisor)	2022 - 2024	
FIRSTDUST		
Young Investigator Program, Villum Foundation, €700K (PI)	2016 - 2021	
Gas to stars - Stars to Dust; Exploring the star formation activity through cosmic time		
National Science Foundation, GROW program (US) €150K (co-PI)	2019 - 2020	
DARK/Carlsberg Independent Research Fellowship €350K (PI)	2015 - 2018	
THALES Programme, ≤ 521 K (co-I)	2012 - 2015	
The invisible side of formation and evolution of supermassive Black Holes in the Universe		
Astrophysical Data Analysis Program, NASA, \$116K (co-I)	2012	
Extreme silicate absorbers in WISE		

MANAGEMENT

Cosmic DAWN Center 2018 - present

 ${\it Co-founder / Deputy \ Director / \ Chair \ of \ the \ Cosmic \ DAWN \ Fellowship \ Program}$

Villum Young Investigator Program (YIP) and YIP+ 2016 - present

Group leader (\sim 3-5 members on average)

Technical University of Denmark

2018 - present

2019 - 2021

MSc course co-ordinator

Scientific strategy committee for DTU-Space A&A

SPICA space telescope

Science co-ordinator of "The co-evolution of black holes and star formation" working group

Telescope observing campaigns PI of >20 international projects 2015 - present

PUBLICATIONS

180 peer reviewed publications, 14 as a first author, 46 as PI/co-PI

Citations: > 18000 (13500), h-index: 69 (63) - Google Scholar (NASA/ADS).

TELESCOPE TIME - PI & CO-I

JWST (~ 130hrs), ALMA(> 600hrs), VLT/Keck/Subaru(~ 60 nights), NOEMA/VLA(> 800hrs), **Herschel**(GTO)

SUPERVISION

MSc/BSc Thesis (14), PhD Thesis (8), Post-Docs (9)

MAIN INTERNATIONAL COLLABORATIONS AND PROJECTS

Major International Collaborations University of Oxford (UK)*Caltech, Harvard University, University of Texas, NOAO (USA)*CEA/Saclay (FR)*MPE, ESO (Germany)

Major International Projects/Teams ALCS*REQUIEM*BUFFALO*PEP*GOODS* HerMES*CLS *KROSS*COSMOS*Candels-H*Cosmic Dawn Survey*SPICA*Euclid

INTERNATIONAL RECOGNITION AND AWARDS - SELECTED

Science and Technology Facilities Council (STFC) Grant Reviewer	2020
SPICA Space Telescope Mission Co-ordinator of the high redshift science case	2019
Enhanced Eurotalents, Grant Reviewer	2017
NASA Astrophysical Data Analysis Program, Selection Committee	2017
ESO, Time Allocation Committee	2017-2018
ERC Starting Grant, Proposal Referee	2016
Royal Astronomical Society Group Achievement Award	2014
SOC of >10 International Conferences	2010 - $present$
42 Invited/Contributed Talks / 17 Colloquia	2010 - present

PRESS RELEASES (PR) AND OUTREACH - MOST RECENT

Astronomy on TAP/Copenhagen	$2021 ext{-}present$
Nature A Supermassive Black Hole Precursor Lurking in Archival Hubble Data	2022
Nature The mystery of early massive galaxies running on empty	2021
Nature Giant galaxy is almost as old as the Universe itself	2020
ApJ A Distant dusty galaxy hidden in plain sight	2019
Nature Unexpectedly large gas in $z > 1.4$ passive galaxies	2018